Guide to the Joel G. Colton papers, 1942-2002
Duke University. University Archives
Joel G. Colton papers 1942-2002
Duke University. University Archives
Colton, Joel G., 1918-.
8.5 linear feet Extent: 8,000 Items
Joel G. Colton (b. 1918), Professor of History and administrator at Duke University (1947-1974, 1982- ). Collection contains correspondence, course materials, writings, clippings, committee materials, subject files, and research notes of Colton.
UA.29.02.0015
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Joel G. Colton papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer 1967-2002, and 2011.
Biographical Note
Joel George Colton was born in New York, N.Y., on August 23, 1918. He earned a B.A. from the City College of New York in 1937 and a M.A. from Columbia University in 1940. From 1942 to 1946, Colton served in the U.S. Army and as a Military Intelligence Officer. He returned to Columbia University and earned a Ph. D. in 1950. Colton joined the faculty of Duke University in 1947, as an instructor in the Department of History. He taught at Duke University until 1974, when he became the Director for Humanities of the Rockefeller Foundation. Colton returned to Duke in 1982 as a Professor of History, specializing in modern European history. Throughout his career at Duke University, Colton held several administrative posts, including Chairman of the Department of History (1967-1974) and Chairman of the Academic Council (1971-1973). He authored numerous articles and books, notably Léon Blum: Humanist in Politics (New York: Knopf, 1966) and A History of the Modern World with R. R. Palmer (New York: Knopf, 1956).
Collection Overview
Correspondence, course materials, writings, clippings, committee materials, subject files, and research notes of Joel G. Colton relating to his teaching and administration at Duke University, military service, education, awards, and publications.
Subject Headings
Colton, Joel G., 1918-; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Dept. of History; Rockefeller Foundation
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 11 Boxes
  - Encyclopedia Americana (Box 1)
  - American Historical Association, Pacific Coast branch (Box 1)
  - Time Life (Box 1)
  - Educational Testing Service (Box 1)
  - Koren Prize Committee, Society for French Historical Studies (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council (Box 1)
  - Encyclopedia Americana (Box 2)
  - American Historical Association (Box 2)
  - Faculty Discussion Group (Box 2)
  - Director of Undergraduate Studies, correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Festschrift (Box 2)
  - University Research Council (Box 2)
  - University Research Council (Box 3)
  - Society for French Historical Studies (Box 3)
  - Herbert Baxter Adams Prize Committee, American Historical Association (Box 3)
  - Southern Historical Association (Box 3)
  - International Relations Committee (Box 3)
  - Meeting of Cultures, typescript (Box 4)
  - Graduate students, correspondence, recommendations [removed] (Box 4)
  - Souvenirs sur d'Affaire (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (Box 5)
  - Academic Council (Box 5)
  - Alfred Tischendorf Memorial Fund (Box 6)
  - Colton-Cordle course (Box 6)
  - Educational Testing Service, Advanced Placement (Box 6)
  - Course on European labor (Box 7)
  - Souvenirs sur d'Affaire (Box 7)
  - Léon Blum material (Box 8)
  - Publications Board, 1965-1968 (Box 9)
  - Blackburn Committee, 1964-1970 (Box 9)
  - A History of the Modern World, revisions (Box 10)
  - Léon Blum material (Box 10)
  - Wartime correspondence, August 1942 - June 1946 (Box 11)
  - R. R. Palmer correspondence (Box 11)
  - Mayflower Award, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Publications (Box 11)
  - Clippings (Box 11)
  - France: Older Clippings (Box 12)
  - France: French Socialist Party (Box 12)
  - France: Current Clippings (Box 12)
  - Origins of Modern and Contemporary Art (Box 12)
  - France: Oct. 2002 Lecture (Box 12)
  - France Today in Historical Perspective (Box 12)
  - Joan of Arc (Box 12)
  - Alumni College Abroad (Box 12)
  - The Avignon Papacy (Box 12)
  - French Revolution: Some Clippings and Monographs (Box 12)
  - Journal of Interdisciplinary History: Article (Box 13)
  - "Germany Today" (Box 13)
  - Stuttgart International Historical Congress (Box 13)
  - Western Society for French History (Box 13)
  - Honoring Bob Paxton's Works on Vichy (Box 13)
  - Academic American Encyclopedia (Box 13)
  - Biographical Dictionary of Internationalists (Box 13)
  - Aspen Institute Executive Seminar (Box 13)
  - Ideas of Progress: Article (Box 13)
  - Teaching Materials (Box 13)
  - Morocco (Box 13)
  - Commission Internationale d'Histoire des Mouvements Sociaux et des Structures Sociales (Box 13)
  - International Congress of Historical Sciences (Box 13)
  - Technology, Economy, and Society (Box 13)
  - Japanese Translation of Colton Book (Box 13)
  - Book Review (Box 13)
  - Intellectual History in the 1980s (Box 13)
  - Youth and Youth Movements (Box 13)
  - American Bibliographical Center Historical Abstracts (Box 13)
  - Progress and Its Discontents: Off Prints (Box 13)
  - Blum Psychoanalysis and History Exam (Box 13)
  - Blum Glossy Print (Box 13)
  - Blum AHA Article (Box 13)
  - Book Review (Box 13)
  - Colton Oral History Interview Transcript, 1975 (Box 13)
  - Léon Blum: Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 14)
  - Poetry (Box 14)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 14)
  - Materials Used for Paper at SFWS Milwaukee Session (Box 14)
  - Correspondence: Palmer-Colton (Box 14)
  - Selected Correspondence on Contract Negotiations (Box 14)
  - Pocket Watch Illustration (Box 14)
  - Chinese Translation of A History of the Modern World (Box 14)
  - Translations other than Chinese (Box 14)
  - New Directions in History (Box 14)
  - The Historian Looks at the Twentieth Century World (Box 14)
  - Of Time and Chance in History (Box 14)
  - Foundations and Historians (Box 14)
  - Commencement Talk to New Ph.D.s (Box 14)
  - The Humanities: Perspectives and Prospects (Box 14)
  - Transformation of the Idea of Progress (Box 14)
  - Intellectual History in the 1980s (Box 14)
  - The Revolutionary Changes of Our Times (Box 14)
  - Two Bicentennials (Box 14)
  - How Historians Will View the Twentieth Century (Box 14)
  - The Idea of Progress in History (Box 14)
  - Humanities Program History (Box 15)
  - World War II Articles (Box 15)
  - Reminiscences: Military History, Correspondence and Source Material (Box 15)
  - Correspondence and Clippings (Box 15)
  - US Army Questionnaire (Box 15)
  - Items of Interest, Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - French Connections (Box 15)
  - Memoir Talk about Bob Palmer and a History of the Modern World (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Materials: Palmer and History of the Modern World (Box 15)
  - Bucharest International Congress of Historical Sciences (Box 15)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholars Program (Box 15)
  - Blum-Mitterrand (Box 15)
  - Introduction: Blum-Mitterrand (Box 15)
  - Talk on Charles de Gaulle (Box 15)
  - Speech/Talk on Léon Blum (Box 15)